Welcome back to the discussion
of spatial networks.
In last video, we were looking
at physical data model level.
This video, we'll continue that discussion
and go from data structures to algorithms.
Broadly, in database terms,
the query processing.
So at the end of this video,
we will learn a little bit about query
processing mindset for managing graphs.
In particular, look for
the building blocks.
The query processing cannot optimize for
everything, but they try to
find common building blocks which are
frequently used, and optimize for that.
And then we'll go into further depth for
one building block
called connectivity query, all right,
and show you two algorithms.
So again, you know, big picture,
we are looking at Spatial Networks.
We saw a Conceptual Model,
Logical Model, and
now we are into Physical Model, and in
particular, we are looking at algorithms.
So let's first, you know,
put the query processing hat and
try to see how databases think.
So one of the interesting part of
databases is that they look at
the workload, and then,
you know, across many,
many queries, they try to look for
commonality, right?
If they can find a common building block,
they optimize it
very well with multiple algorithms,
data structures, and so on, right?
So the same thinking with networks,
you know,
if we did that, then we do look for
building blocks.
For each building block, we'll put some
algorithms, sometimes called strategies,
and then when a new query comes we'll
decompose into building blocks and
then rank these algorithms and
pick the most suitable one, okay.
This is sort of like, you know, if you
drive automatic transmission car you just
put it in drive and the car picks
whether it's first gear, second gear or
third gear based on the need and the same
way databases are like automatic car.
Very different from a Java programming,
where you have to pick algorithm, right?
Okay, so
if we were to do this with graphs,
then people think of at least two
common queries, one is connectivity.
So essentially, given a road map, or
a train network, we simply want to know
whether we can reach point A from point B.
This may look very trivial to
you because you might say,
well the network should be
designed that way and many are.
But, you know,
if you are in an island nation this,
you may have to think about it.
But, more importantly, there are other
Spatial Networks like electric circuits.
So, if you think of the power grid and,
you know, there is an outage after
a storm and this is an important query.
The other one you probably expected,
shortest path; so
shortest path turns out
to be a work horse.
Not only it's useful in itself, but
it helps up with many other queries,
such as allocating customers to nearest
service center and so on, okay?
So many times we think about essentially
having multiple algorithm for
these building blocks.
So that, you know,
depending on the situation,
we can have good performance, Okay?
So there are many algorithms, you know,
so many of you might have
seen main memory algorithms.
For example, given that matrix or decency
list representation, we can use algorithms
like depth first search or breadth first
search to check the connectivity right.
And same thing for shortest paths some of
you probably took a data structures and
algorithms course and you may have
come across Dijkstra's shortest path
algorithm it's also thought in
operations research geography and so on.
Those of you who might, you know, have
taken artificial intelligence course might
have seen another algorithm called A-star,
and
we will at least look at these
two in our discussion, okay.
Now it turns out that, you know,
if your data is primarily on disk, some of
these algorithms have to be adjusted for
the higher cost, and in addition,
there are specialized algorithms,
like Hierarchical routing, which tries to
look at only a part of the graph to
reduce IU and still give the optimality.
And we'll try to see if
we have time to go and
visit that, but the first,
the main memory one are worth reviewing.
So also good news is, that SQL3, you know
with the cursive statement has been in
place, and they have adopted some of
these algorithms for use within SQL3.
So let's look at two algorithms for
one building block that's
connectivity queried.
So in case of connectivity query,
given a particular graph and a particular
start node, we want to list all of
the nodes which are reachable from there.
And the used cases may be in a smart
grid electricity network to see
whether power from a particular generating
station can reach all the customers, or
in a road map after hurricane of flooding,
we might want to see from a,
let's say relief supply
distribution center, you know,
which particular people needing
help can we serviced, okay.
So let's first look at Breadth
first search, you know,
and suppose the starting node is one.
So in case of Breadth first search,
we visit other nodes level by level.
So we first reach the nodes
which are directly connected.
So from 1, nodes 2 and
4 can be reached first because
there is a direct edge, right.
Once we have reached nodes 2 and 4,
then we try to visit the next set of nodes
which are reachable within two edges.
So from node 2 we can reach node 3,
and from 4 we can reach node 5.
So essentially, your traversals goes
by level by level, starting with 1.
We first go to 2, 4, and then 3, 5, okay.
The order within level
is not really dictated.
You can visit them in any order.
The second algorithm is Depth
first search, and in this case,
we essentially follow one path till we
hit a dead end and then trace back.
Something, you know,
you might have experienced in
solving a maze kind of puzzle, okay.
So, let's say we start with node 1, and
let's suppose we go down node 2,
the first edge.
Then once we added node 2,
we might visit something whichever by 2,
which might be node 3 or node 4.
Let's suppose you have end down node 3,
right, and node 3 is a dead end.
We can't go anywhere further,
so we go back to node 2, and
we say is there anywhere
else we can reach?
And we see node 4 right,
and then we continue on and
from 4 we can reach 5 and
then we backtrack, okay.
So the order is different.
So again give you the visual contrast,
let's compare these two
algorithms iteration by
iteration in the order of visit.
So suppose we started with node 1.
In the first iteration both algorithms
may go to a common node, right,
which is node 2,
because those are reachable by one edge.
But in the next iteration you
start to see the difference.
The, the Breadth first search goes to node
4 which is one edge away, it prefers that,
whereas Depth first search is now going
to node 3, which may be two edges away.
And then subsequent iteration again
you will see the behavior change, and
you essentially see some
differences between the two.
So with this we'll wrap up
the discussion of basic introduction to
query processing and
also algorithms for connectivity query.
When we come back in the next video,
we'll look at two algorithms for
shortest pathway.
Thank you, looking forward
to seeing you soon [SOUND].