Welcome back to the discussion
of spatial networks.
And so far we've looked at
the societal use cases and
motivation for
learning about spatial networks.
You know, for example all of us use
navigation apps on smartphone or
on web based services like Google Maps.
We also looked at conceptual
models of spatial network.
We looked at en,
an entity relationship diagram.
But also graph models,
which have very nice mathematical and
computational properties.
So in this video,
we are going to start discussion of the
logical data model for spatial networks.
So at the end of this video,
we should be able to describe the need for
extensions to the SQL spatial querying
language we have learned so far.
And also specify specific details such as
the recursive querying facility in SQL.
So there is different ways to extend and
we can list them.
All right so
clicks again recall the context,
you know we have discussed conceptual data
model and this case we are in a video.
We are going to look at logical data
model and we look at two different ways
to extend SQL to support queries on
spatial networks such as shortest path.
And in subsequent videos we will see
the details of those two ways and
then we'll come back and
look at physical data model,
how to perform these queries very,
very efficiently on large networks.
Okay, so first let's look at a basic
notion called Transitive Closure.
Because this is one way to formally
describe the limitations of traditional
query languages, including the spatial
querying we have learned so far, okay?
So consider a graph G which has a set
a vertices V and a set of edges E.
Then Transitive Closure of this graph
is described as another graph G star.
And it has a set of vertices V star,
another set of edges E star, okay.
And formally, the set of vertices is same
as the set of vertices in original graph.
So V and V star are the same.
But the set of edges is much richer.
So not only we have the original edges,
but we also add all the paths.
To illustrate this,
let's look at a very simple graph.
So here we have a graph with about five
nodes, one, two, three, four, five.
And you also see five edges, okay.
So this is your basic graph G.
Now if we were to look at its Transitive
Closure it will have same set of nodes, so
five nodes, but many more edges.
Which will represent all possible parts,
okay?
So here if you look at G star,
so five nodes and nine edges.
And here is the picture of that, okay?
So you see the same five nodes show up
here but the set of edges is richer.
Okay?
So where did they come from?
They are essentially listing the,
all possible paths.
So, for example,
notice in the original graph,
we could go from node one to node four,
but there was no direct edge.
In order to reach there, you either
had to go through five, three, and
four, or via two, three, and four, okay.
But nonetheless,
there is a path from one to four.
So in the Transitive Closure you
see an edge from one to four.
Okay?
So all possible paths have been listed,
okay?
So this path 1, 2, 3, 4, for
example, is listed as 1, 4.
You can also see it in a tabular manner.
Okay.
Now you probably realize that
the shortest pathway that we
all used to on Google Maps and
on your smartphone nav applications.
Are examples of Transitive Closure.
Okay.
But
in addition to shortest path there
are other Transitive Closure operations.
For example if you're looking
at the electric network then you
might see connectivity.
Okay.
Will the current flow from point A to B,
that's another example
of Transitive Closure.
Okay.
So why are we talking about
all this Transitive Closure?
Okay, the reason is that if you remember
the spatial querying we learned so far.
It was based on relational algebra.
And there is a formal result, which
basically says that the Original SQL, and
other relational algebra
based query languages.
Are not able to compute
transitive closures.
So in other words if you wanted to support
the shortest path using the spatial query
language we learned so far with
operations like select, project and join.
We were out of luck.
Okay.
Unless we knew the length of the path.
If you know your path length
is limited to five or ten.
You could use a sequence of those five or
ten joins.
But if we don't know the path length a
priori, there is no way to do that, okay.
In other words,
we need to extend our query languages
to support transitive closure.
So this discussion happened quite
a bit in late 80s and early 90s.
And people looked at
many different choices.
And here are the two basic
choices which are possible.
So one mechanism to extend query
languages is via abstract data type.
And this is how we extended basic SQL3 to
support spatial data types like points,
lines, strings, polygons.
And we spent a lot of time in, you know,
in previous spatial query language
discussion to illustrate that.
'Kay?
Now the same mechanism can be
used to support spatial networks.
If we can design a set of abstract data
types, then we could add it to SQL3.
Okay?
What may these data types be?
We'll come back and
see the details in next video.
But you can imagine data types
like graphs, nodes, vertices, or
maybe even paths.
What kind of operations
we may want on those.
Certainly shortest path will be one
of them, connectivity, and so on.
Okay, so if we could design
these abstract data types,
then SQL3 is capable of
incorporating those.
And then you will be able to use the
existing select statement to query graphs.
Okay.
However, there's another way
to extend query languages and
those are custom statements.
And SQL has gone actually that way.
So first the vendors were making
their own custom statements.
So, for example in Oracle.
You will find, Oracle SQL,
you will find a statement called CONNECT.
And this was created for directed acyclic
graphs or hierarchies because many,
many companies have trees, for
example to to present build of materials,
you know, what ingredients do I need to
produce a particular food product, okay?
And they often want a transitive
closure on these hierarchies.
So Oracle added this statement, and
it's little bit easier to implement
than general graph, okay?
These are not going to help
you on shortest path and
road networks,
because road networks have cycles, right?
So a more general approach
was taken with SQL3
to add another statement
called the WITH RECURSIVE.
And that supports general graph and
transitive closure such as
shortest path on general graphs.
So when you come back in next video,
we will look at the details
of these statements.
And and then, go back and,
see how to implement them efficiently in
the discussion of physical data models.
So thank you for your attention, I hope
this video showed you the limitations of
traditional query languages and
motivated you to learn some new features
which can support spatial network queries.
And look forward seeing you to discuss
the details of these in the next videos.
Thank you.
[SOUND]