Welcome back to the discussion
of spacial networks.
In last four videos we looked
at the societal motivation.
For example many of us use
navigation apps on our smartphones.
Also via web services such as google maps.
Underlining these applications we have
many spacial networks such as road maps,
public transportation,
networks, and so on.
We also looked at conceptual data
models called spatial networks.
For example,
we looked at entity relationship diagram,
which can represent
a rich set of concepts.
For example, in road map one may
represent streets street intersections,
turns, points of interest, and so on.
Mathematically we use a simpler
model called graphs which
essentially consists a set of vertices or
nodes and another set of edges.
In case of road maps, the vertices
made project road into sections.
And the edges made a project
road segment connecting those.
Okay?
Now next we started looking at
logical data models, primarily for
creating road maps.
And we discussed why, you know,
the SQL we have learned so
far, the spatial equating we have
learned so far, is not adequate.
Okay, formally, relational algebra cannot
represent so you need some new things.
So in this video module we are going
to learn one extension to SQL
to equate graphs.
So at the end of this video
we should all be able to
describe the connect clause in SQL Select.
It's a render specific feature.
Oracle was the one who
started this feature,
then maybe other brand names
which may also have it.
And using CONNECT we'll also learn how
the query a directed acyclic graph.
Okay.
So here is your, you know,
quick background.
You remember for querying we learned that
our tradition SQL, which is based on
relational algebra, is not capable
of computing transitive closure.
In other words if I gave you
road segments connecting
existing intersections we cannot
express shortest path query in old SQL.
So we need to extend SQL to support
graph queries such as shortest path and
there are two broad ways to do that.
One could use abstract data type in
SQL 3 very much like the data type,
points, polygons et cetera,
we use for spatial equating.
One could define graphs and
paths, vertices, edges, and so.
Okay.
The other approach is to add
custom statements in SQL and
we will start from there first.
Okay.
So there at least two different
ways people have done it.
We'll look at the original, you know,
CONNECT by you know, CONNECT clause in
SELECT statement that was popularized by
Oracle and then, in the subsequent video,
we will come back and look at recursion,
which is standardized with SQL 3.
Okay?
So, without further ado,
let's look at the CONNECT BY facility, and
in this slide we are going to
look at the input and output.
And as you recall, you know,
the goal is to compute transitive closure.
So import is a graph more specifically
a directed acyclic graph.
So for example, here we are showing you
the river network represented as a graph,
where the nodes are rivers,
such as here you see Missouri,
Mississippi, and the edges, or
directed edges, represent falls into.
So Missouri falls into Mississippi and
that's this edge.
Okay.
Given such a graph,
the connect by statement can,
you know compute transitive closure.
In addition, it can actually give
you a sub-set of transitive closure.
So for example,
you can specify a start node.
Let's say we started with Missouri.
Then we can do two kinds of queries.
Either predecessors of Missouri or
successors of Missouri.
Okay.
So in order to separate those you need
to also specify travel direction.
Okay.
So essentially if you wanted to compute
predecessor, then, you know, you will
get all these rivers which directly or
indirectly contribute water to Missouri.
And in this case,
you're travel direction is in some
sense is opposite of these arrows.
Okay?
The other option is to find
Successors of Missouri,
in which case we are following the arrows
as their projected in their diagram and
in this case you might find
Mississippi as a successor.
Missouri contributes water to that river.
Let's next look at
the tabular representation.
Because in SQL all the data has
to be represented as tables.
So one way to represent graphs in terms of
tables is to simply list the edges, okay.
Okay?
So
here is an edge table for
this river falls into another river graph.
And in this case we may
just need two columns.
Because each edge has its, you know,
it starts from its source and
it ends up at the destination.
So for example, if you're looking at
the edge, Missouri falls into Mississippi.
We may specify as a row, where Source is
Missouri, and Destination is Mississippi.
Now, if I look at the other way around,
you know Platte and
Yellowstone, they fall into Missouri.
In this course Missouri may
be their destination, and
those rivers may be their source.
Okay?
So if I actually created one row for
each of these edges, then you are going to
get two more rows, like this Ohio etc.,
falling into Mississippi.
They are here, and remaining, you know,
contributories to Missouri are here.
So once you have this tabular
representation we can work with SQL or
and we can look at the,
the syntax of this statement.
Okay?
So
here is a very simple
example of CONNECT BY.
'Kay?
So in this particular SELECT statement,
you would recall some familiar things.
So for example, you know,
there is a SELECT clause and a FROM cause.
These two we saw before when we
were studying spatial equating.
And you will remember that the FROM
clause specifies the table, okay.
So in our case let's say we are working
with this table Falls_Into to
representing our graph.
That table may named in the FROM clause.
Very much like the other SQL statements
we saw where we were listing tables.
'Kay?
Then we have two new clauses,
this CONNECT BY and
START WITH, and
let's try to understand what they do.
START WITH is a much simpler clause.
And in this case,
you notice it specifies a column in
our table, so destination column.
And it also provides a condition.
So it's saying that, you know,
you should start with the rows in this
table, where the destination is Missouri.
So these two rows are the starting point.
And starting with these rows,
we could either try to find predecessors
of Missouri or successors of Missouri.
Okay?
So now a natural question is,
what does connect by prior clause do?
And you can probably guess,
it is specifying the direction of travel.
Starting with Missouri, do you want
the successors, or predecessor?
Okay?
So in other words, you know,
if you think about this red arrow, if you
want to go from destination to source.
In other words, getting predecessor.
You know, which reverse
contribute water to Missouri.
Then you could specify this and
as it is shown in this statement.
So in fact,
this prior is placed before source, so
it basically says you are going
from destination to source, okay?
We could move this keyword prior to
other side after the equal sign and that
will give you the other direction where
you're going from source to destination.
And then sometimes this ad was
going the other way, okay.
So so let's look at both side by side.
If you are going from destination
to source, or, you know,
this should be source to destination,
slight typo.
The so, contributing reverts to Missouri,
in this case,
so now that you might see as
the query we just saw, okay.
So this query is going to
start with Missouri and
get to the rivers which directly
contribute to Missouri, and
it will continue on and say any river that
contributes to these rivers, Platte or
Yellowstone, are also contributing
to Missouri main directory.
Okay.
The second choice is to
ask the successors of
Missouri which rivers
get water from Missouri.
So if there were, let's say,
a spill of some toxic material
in Mississippi in Missouri.
And you want to ask which of
the rivers should be observed or
monitored for that material,
then you will go the other direction.
And notice here the prior keyword
has been moved past the equal sign.
Okay?
So here the direction is
from source to destination,
this is a typo, but this is the other
direction as shown in the figure.
Okay?
So next let's look at the semantics.
Okay.
As you know SQL is a declarative language.
It doesn't specify any algorithms
to compute the result.
But we can at least create a mock up
algorithm which is for hand simulation so
that you can understand the meaning of
a given statement with connect by clause.
Okay?
So let's suppose we go back to this
statement which we have seen before.
Where, you know, you are looking
back at this table FallsInto and
then you want to travel it
in a certain direction.
And then get either places,
several successors.
Okay?
So in order to execute it.
The first step, usually,
is to work with this initialization.
This START WITH clause is executed first.
So in this case, you know,
if you look at the query,
you know, the condition destination equal
to Missouri, that will qualify two rows,
which are surrounded by blue box here,
okay.
So we'll initialize the result
with just these two rows.
Okay, so this is your result or
you can call it the prior result
because it's going to grow.
Okay?
So if the first steps we get
two rows where destination is
Missouri as specified by
this start with clause.
Okay.
Once we have done that then
we can grow the result.
And at that point,
this connect by clause comes in handy.
So, in the next step, we basically
look at this connect by clause, and
this condition, and
we try to grow the desert.
So, more formally, what you can do
is to think of this prior, you know,
dot source equal to the original
table FallsInto.destination as
a joint condition.
'Kay.
So in other words, you know, you can
take a look at the prior source, okay.
In our results so far there are two
sources, Platte and Yellowstone.
And now we go back to our
original table FallsInto and
say what do they match on
their destination side.
Okay.
As specified here.
So in this case as you can see it will
match four rows in original table.
And then all of these four rows will come
and become part of your result, okay.
So all of this will get added and now
your result has the original two rows and
four new rows, six rows, okay.
Now step two can be repeated again.
All right.
So now we can again try to say,
well if I took, you know,
all these sources, P1, P2, et cetera, and
try to match it with destination,
will I get more things in the result.
And in this case, as you realize we
are not going to add any more because we
don't have any predecessors
of these new reverse, P1,
P2, et cetera which has been added, okay?
So we will terminate.
And at this point we have
all the rows of interest.
And then finally the select
clause is going to be executed,
which will only take the first column,
the source column, to form the result.
And that's where you get the result.
Okay?
So to summarize you know,
we looked at connect clause which has been
added to select statement by some vendors
like Oracle to support graph queries.
This particular statement allows you
to work with a directed acyclic graph.
So, if you have something hierarchical or
tree-like, then you can travel it,
either travel it up the tree or
down the tree to compute predecessors
of successors of the node.
We also showed you an example
with river network to
explain the syntax and semantics.
In the next video we'll come back and
look at another statement
called with recursive.
Which is more standardized in SQL3 and
may be available across many,
many brand names and, and vendors.
And that will give you a more general
statement to work with graphs.
So look, look forward to
seeing you in the next video.