Welcome back to the discussion
of spacial networks.
In previous video,
we looked at the societal motivation for
studying spacial network and
we saw that there are many,
many use cases,
particularly in an urban society.
All of us use navigation, for
example, on either a web-based or
smart phone based platform, okay?
We also saw the limitations, and we argued
that the spacial equating we learned so
far in the previous week is not
adequate to model these queries on
spacial networks, okay?
In this video segment,
we have very modest goal.
We are just going to look at three simple
examples of spatial networks, okay?
And these will be used for
running examples through all this module.
So, when we come back in later videos,
we will often see these networks and
associated queries being used to
illustrate various ideas, okay?
For example, when we introduce the graph
model, we'll show you the graph
representation of three example networks
from this particular module, okay?
So at the end of this video, we should
all be able to describe at least three
simple spatial networks and
a few queries associated with that, okay?
So let's look at the first one,
which is already quite familiar to us, and
this is a road network.
So on the left we are giving you a very
simple view of road networks, with major
roads in the city of Minneapolis where,
you know, city of Minnesota is located.
It also has, you know, two routes.
So you kind of see a blue line and
a red line, and they are representing two
kinds of shortest path between this upper
left corner and lower right corner.
The, as you can guess, the red line
is probably shortest distance but
the blue line is shortest travel time
as it takes advantage of the freeway.
Highway 94 in this case, okay?
So types of queries yet, again,
are probably familiar to you.
The very fast one we already talked about.
We may ask for a shorted path.
So given a starting location, maybe in
Residio, Minnesota, and a destination,
maybe the airport, we may ask, what is the
shortest path to reach there, either for
distance or travel time and so on, okay?
But there are other queries of interest.
Again, you know, like location-based
services, if you have access to that.
You could also ask for near, nearest
instance of facilities from our location.
Let's imagine you were in computer science
building at University of Minnesota and
it is lunch time, and you are looking for
any rest, you know, restaurant.
You could ask for that query.
Or, for some reason, you wanted to
get a flu shot, you could ask for
the nearest hospital and so on.
A third query may be including
a set of destinations.
So we saw this from the business
context in network analysis.
Here, you know it's there may be a
starting point like a store and they have
to deliver a set of, you know, furniture
to many, many houses and they may ask for
a route, which covers all theses houses
and minimizes the total distance, okay?
And, finally, you know,
we also looked at allocate query.
So, let's say you have a set
of service centers maybe many,
many retail stores, and you have a set of,
of customers, and you are assigning
customers to the nearest store.
So, you could define service areas or
number of customers likely to easiest
reach your store and so on, okay?
All right, so let's switch and
look at a very different network,
which may be less familiar to
some of us if, unless you live in
urban area which has public transportation
such as train networks, okay?
So here,
we are showing you a subway network.
In Minneapolis areas right now,
we have a very simple network,
just one line, so it's not as interesting.
In next few years,
we may have more lines and use that.
So we are showing you a network
from San Francisco area.
It's called BART, and it has, you know, in
this map, it's showing four lines, okay?
So you can kind of see one line going from
top right to bottom left, and so on, okay?
The colors are not shown, but
they are listed in the text,
if you could zoom in you will see.
So, you know, this particular
route is Yellow West, you know,
it's shown in yellow arrow here.
And then one could do a very
simple aggregate query here.
You could say on Yellow West route, tell
me how many stations are located, okay?
So one could count and
see how many route, you know,
stations these, shown as black
dots are covered by this, okay?
Another query, you know, may have
to do with a particular stop, okay?
So in subway network usually you
have routes and you have stop.
And one interesting stop here is Berkeley,
downtown, which is number two.
It's shown as that red square here.
And we may ask questions like, you know,
which other stops are reachable
from Berkley, okay?
Hopefully, if it is a rich network it
would reach all of them
by switching trains.
So, you could ask whether
you can reach it directly or
do you have to change trains, okay?
Now, in addition to that, you could
still do the shortest path queries.
So, here we are showing you another
destination called Daley city, and
here is Berkeley.
And you could ask, give me the routes
which connect a particular start point
such as Downtown Berkeley and
a destination such as Daley city.
Okay and then finally,
we could ask for, you know,
some other aggregate
queries on certain routes.
So here is a blue route, Blue West,
and we can ask for the first stop or
last stop, okay?
So these are subway
network kind of queries.
Let's look at a third network.
And again, you know, if you, unless you
have worked with natural resources or
you're a geography enthusiast
it maybe a little bit new, okay?
So here we are showing you
a natural network of rivers.
You know this map is showing you some of
the major rivers in the United States.
For example, Mississippi River
starts in the state of Minnesota,
and then kind of flows south to
New Orleans and then Gulf of Mexico, okay?
But on the way it pick up
water from many tributaries.
So on the way it pick up from Missouri,
Colorado, Platte and so on, okay?
Oh, not Colorado,
Colorado was the other way.
But, you know,
you have a set of river networks and
it's interesting to know which river
falls into which other river and
that could be modeled as
a spatial network, okay?
So, types of queries here may
be of the following kind.
So you could ask, you know,
for a river Mississippi.
You know, list all the other rivers
which contribute water to Mississippi,
which are tributaries to Mississippi.
And in this answer, Colorado will not be
included, because it goes the other way.
But you will have Missouri and
other rivers, okay?
We may ask other questions,
because sometimes, you know,
these rivers may contribute
water directly by falling or
merging with a river or
sometimes they may be indirect.
So, you could separate them out and
just ask for direct tributaries, okay?
Now if you're interested in,
in emergency management and
so on, then a common query is to,
you know, take care of pollutions.
So sometimes you have train lines or
there are other incidents,
there are farms next to rivers, and
occasionally, accidents happen, all right?
So you may have a oil spill, or a
fertilizer spill and then people want to,
essentially, inform everyone
downstream about water quality.
In case they were using it for
drinking water or
other uses, they may have to take
precaution and stop that, right?
That there has been similar incident
in east coast North Carolina recently.
so, so given a particular spill,
we may want to ask a question about
all the rivers that may get affected.
And then from there,
you can inform the communities, okay?
So this is a third kind of network and
slightly different questions.
So just to sum up, you know,
we saw three different spatial networks.
A road network, a train network,
and a river network.
And on each we saw some questions, okay?
And these were mixed questions.
Some of them required
transitive closure and
recursion and will need new knowledge
that we will learn in this chapter.
And somewere very simple like aggregate
queries that you could have answered using
spatial query.
And it may be a good exercise for
you to go back to those questions and
ask yourself which of these you can
answer easily using spatial query, and
where do we need new knowledge.
So well, this we'll wrap up
this particular video segment.
When we come back,
we'll introduce mathematical model and
information model for spatial networks.
So that you can answer all
of these queries, okay?
So looking forward to seeing you in the,
the next set of video segments.
Thank you.