Welcome back to the discussion
of spatial networks.
In our previous two videos, we primarily
looked at the multivision, and
we saw that spatial networks
are societally very important.
Many of us already have already used
them in navigation applications on
our smartphone as well as on web
services like Google Maps, okay?
What we want to do now is to go under
the hood and see how these networks
are modeled computationally and then
how do we design scalable algorithms so
that we can compute spatial network
queries like shortest path very quickly,
even on roadmaps spanning the entire
country or the whole world, okay?
So at the end of this module,
we should be able to talk about
conceptual models of spatial networks.
In a later video module we'll
come back and look at logical and
physical model as well.
And in particular we are going
to look at Graph models, okay?
That is something which has nice
mathematical properties, and
has been investigated in computer
science for a long time, and
it's a very popular computational
model of spatial networks, okay?
So the big picture,
essentially in this video and
the next two videos, we are going to look
at different models of spatial network,
in this particular case we
are looking at conceptual model.
So we'll look at conceptual
model at two level,
one is the conceptual model
from database perspective,
It's often called the entity relationship
diagram and we saw a similar model in
spatial query chapter, describing the data
sets involving country, river, and cities.
In this chapter,
we are going to describe road networks and
spatial networks using this too.
But the main focus would be to
understand the mathematical model
called graph because that's widely
used both in mathematics and
in software to model spatial networks.
After this video when we come back to next
video, we'll look at logical data model,
in some sense the facilities for creating
it, as well as physical data model.
How do we stores networks so that we can
scale up to very large networks, okay?
So without further ado,
let's take a look at one of
the spatial networks many of
us are familiar with, right?
Probably most of us have used road
maps in navigation application.
So here'd we are showing
a small picture office.
A tiny section of a road map near
the University of Minnesota in
an area called Dinky Town.
So, you might actually
recognize this cartography.
You know, very typical of Google Maps.
And here you see roads like 4th Street
which is sort of going from the right side
to the left side or 5th Street which
is going from left to the right.
University Avenue which again,
going from East to West.
But you also see these avenues,
5th Avenue and 6th Avenue.
This is 5th and 6th which are going
sort of North-South direction.
Now, if you were to model this is using,
entity-relationship diagram,
then we often ask about the concepts which
people used to think about roadmaps.
So common concepts include the notion
of roads, streets, and avenues.
And we already illustrate, illustrated
many of those a few seconds ago, okay?
But in addition people talk
about road intersection, so for
example you know when you
look at University Avenue and
it intersects with 7th Avenue Southeast,
this may be an intersection, okay?
So here is another intersection, okay?
Where 6th Avenue and
5th Street intersect, okay?
Another common concept is segment.
Once we have the notion
of road intersection,
then people often decompose a road or
a street into smaller pieces.
So for example, you know if you
look at this intersection and
that intersection then the segment of
5th Street, just this little piece
that connects adjacent road intersection
is often thought of as a road segment.,
okay, and so on.
Another concept that we will
use is the notion of turns.
And if you have driven in urban areas,
you might have encountered
many turn restrictions.
You know, it may say no left turn at this
intersection if you're coming from north,
or no right turn if you're
coming from south and so on.
Some of these turn restrictions may
be due to one-way nature of the road,
all right, and other may be imposed
just to make the traffic flow smoothly.
And so on, so there are many,
many concepts we used when
dealing with road maps.
And all these concepts can be put together
into an entity relationship diagram.
So we'll quickly show you
a very big picture, you know
high level set of concepts that hopefully
you know you have used before and
many of us use in day to day, life.
So first concept is road map.
You know, you may look at a large,
you know, paper map, or you may go to and
look at a digital map.
And this road map as we just talked about,
consists of many,
many road intersections, and
many road segments, okay.
So an entity relationship diagram,
you know, and
you'll see this chicken foot, it's saying
a road map has many road intersections.
And same way a road map
has many road segments,
each road segment may have two road
intersections that it connects, 'kay?
Other interesting concepts are those
of the notion of the streets and
roads themselves, which as you know
are being shown as a box here, and
they can be modeled as a sequence
of road segments, okay?
Turns may also be thought
of as something imposed on
a sequence of road segments, okay?
And same with routes.
If you have your favorite
route from home to work,
again that's often modeled as a sequence
of road segments and intersections, okay?
You know other ideas may
be points of interest.
On a road map,
often certain places of interest
are highlighted such as airports, right?
Or downtowns, schools, and these
are often part of this point of interest,
they often have an address.
In many countries, this address comes
in the form of street address, so you
may give the name of the street and then a
building number on that particular street.
But, you know, this is a new system,
it's only about 100 to 150 years old and
countries like England and
US have gone through a lot of
legislative process to systematize it.
But many other countries we
don't have street address and
there your address may
be much more simpler.
It may be based on a landmark but
if you have a smartphone and GPS,
you can simply provide the latitude and
longitude.
So these addresses may come in many forms,
okay, and so on.
Another concept that we may visit
later is the observational framework.
Nowadays we have lot of sensors on the
road, and these sensors may be static or
moving, and they observe different
properties of the road and so on.
And also in the map you need
some kind of coordinate system.
Latititude longitude is one in
order to specify these locations.
So they are showing you a rich site of
concepts people may use to model roads.
And you know, we have just given
you a few common concepts and
you can probably enrich this
diagram with more concepts.
So let's now switch gears and
look at the, the graph model, okay?
My entity-relationship
diagram was very rich.
It could model many, many concepts.
Graph is a much simpler model, okay?
So let's first look at its
mathematical definition and
then apply it to model roadmaps, okay?
So mathematically graph just is a pair.
Okay, it has two components,
a graph G has two components.
The first symbol, V, stands for
a set of nodes or vertices, okay.
The second symbol, E,
stands for a set of edges.
And they model one binary
relationship among vertices, okay.
So let's illustrate it to see, you know,
if you were to use this to model road map,
what would they look like?
So here is the road map we saw before,
which had many road intersections and
many road segments connecting them.
And one way to model it as a graph is to
use road intersections as the nodes, and
road segments connecting edges and
intersections as the edges.
And if you did that,
the graph model may look like this.
So here you notice, you know,
all these nodes and 7, and 4 and 5.
And these are modeling
road intersections here.
Just to show that correspondence
little bit easier let me
show you an overlay of these two
images and it may look like this.
So you now see these nodes that
we had in the graph they match up
with the road intersection.
And then the edges we have, they match
up with the road segments, okay?
So this is one way to model roadmaps and
graphs, and
it's a popular way to model that, okay?
It's often used for
computing shortest path, okay?
Now, now when you look
at this graph model and
you've tried to compare it with the
entity-relationship model we showed you in
the last, dia, slide,
you probably realized that this graph is
not modeling all the information in
that entity-relationship diagram, right?
So we can do a very quick big picture
comparison of the two models and
try to see the pros and cons, okay.
Before that, we'll also show you
another example of graph model.
If you remember the River Network that
we covered in the previous video,
where you had these major
rivers in United States, and
we had a relationship called falls into.
Okay, that may be modeled
as a graph like this.
So here,
River Mississippi is maybe node 1.
River Missouri maybe node, another node,
and this arrow might show you that this,
you know, large river falls
into another river, okay?
So graph models can be used to model
different spatial networks, but
they are simple, okay?
So going back to the road example, and
if you compare the entity-relationship
diagram for the roads, and the graph model
for the roads, here are the strengths and
weaknesses of graph models, okay?
So in terms of strength graph models
have very, very nice mathematics.
In fact there is a whole branch of
mathematics called graph theory
which has characterized many
properties of the graph and
it has classified graphs
into different kind.
And those properties can help us
reason about graphs very well, okay?
So, for example when we compute shortest
path, this mathematics can help us
tell whether the path returned by our
algorithm is indeed the optimal or
shortest path, or whether it is not, okay?
The second strength is that
the graphs have been very popular in
computer science.
And over the last 50 to 60 years,
computer scientists have designed very
nice algorithms to manipulate graph.
So you know, you,
you have enjoyed the fruits of those.
For example when you go to Google Maps and
compute shortest path,
you probably don't realize how big a graph
it is using to model road map of US.
Okay, that graph has billions of nodes,
and
yet the shortest path is
computed almost instantaneously.
You don't even feel the time it takes,
right?
So those are the nice computational
algorithms that have been designed over
the last 50, 60 years, and we can leverage
those if you use graphs as the model.
Okay, but what's the down side?
Okay, and here is the down side.
If you think about that entity
relationship diagram I showed you,
then graphs are modeling only
a small part of that, okay?
And to be more precise, they are modeling
only one binary relationship, okay?
So if you think of nodes as road
intersections then this relationship could
be that a road segment connects to
a different road intersection, okay?
But if you wanted to model another
relationship, okay, besides connect.
If you want to model, let's say, turn
restriction, then there is a quandary.
Okay, in a graph,
you can only model one relationship well.
Okay, so trying to model two
relationship adds complexity, and
I will illustrate that very quickly.
And in fact, in many traditional graph
theory and graph algorithm scores,
you know, asking for
a shortest path which minimizes turns or
has no left turn often confounds these
computer scientists because that's
a limitation of graph, okay.
Another implication of
this is the following.
Based on your preference for
the relationship, right,
in other words you know if you
look at your dominant queries.
And those, those queries are asking for
you know a different set of
relationships than the one
modeled by popular graph model.
Then, you have limitations.
Either you have to change
your graph model or
look for multiple graph models for
the same road network, okay?
So let's look at an example of both.
So let's first think about turn modeling,
and
we all note modeling turns
are important in road maps.
In fact you might have even seen a recent
New York Times story that a major
logistics company, UPS, you know,
they were looking for new ways to
minimize fuel consumption going beyond
what Google Maps can do for you.
And one of the insights they had was
that their trucks were spending a lot of
time idling on left turns
in the United States, okay?
If you were in Britain, and, you know,
it may be the right turns, but
usually the turns are asymmetric.
One turn usually is quicker because
you don't have to wait, and
the other turn you have to wait for the
opposite traffic to stop for you, okay?
And UPS noticed that and they redid
their routes to reduce left turns in
United States and it saved them
millions of gallons of fuel, okay?
So modeling turns
are important societally.
If you imagine everybody else doing that,
you know,
you could probably reduce fuel
consumption in a much bigger way.
But how do we model that, okay?
So, so if you want to model that,
there are a couple of
different approaches, okay?
One approach is to translate it back
to the basic relationship connects and
some people have tried that, but
it simply expands your graph a lot, so
let me illustrate that.
So if you remember,
you know, this road map.
So you have many one ways here.
So, for example, if you think about this
road intersection between this one-way and
a two-way,
then there are turn restrictions.
For example, you know,
going this, up, like this, we cannot turn
right, right, because that's a one way.
So if you want to model that, you know,
you know, enter, so then what we can do is
to take the intersection N5, modeling
this place, and expand it further.
Okay, expand it further
into a bigger graph, okay?
And in that graph you will have many,
many extra edges modeling
all possible turns, okay?
So, so in this graph, you know,
if, let's say you're going on this
one way, it is going up here.
Then you know, this will allow you
to turn in different direction.
It can take a right turn and you can,
you know, take a left turn, okay?
However if I was going on this road, okay?
If I'm going on this road which
are these two edges, then, you know,
I have a right turn available,
but there is no left turn.
I cannot go back this way.
So that is just missing, okay?
So this is one way to model the turns.
And in this case, your sight of nodes and
edges grows a lot.
So essentially this node N5 now has
been replaced by six different notes and
a bunch of edges, okay?
So if you were to do that,
your graph size will go up.
In addition, doing this is still,
you know, for no U-turn is harder, okay,
because U-turn involves actually
a sequence of more than two edges,
it's three edges.
So, it's a little harder here, okay?
So, there are some other approaches,
as well.
You know, ideally,
we should switch to another notion
called hyper-graphs and hyper-edges.
If you want to model U-turns, you may
have to model three edges, and so on.
And that is very hard to model in
regular graphs but hyper-edges and
hyper-graphs can do that.
Another approach is to
actually go beyond graphs.
So whether you use graphs or
hyper-graphs, we can actually annotate,
we can add some additional information
to nodes like N5, the whole table.
Which lists all possible turns that
there are delays and restrictions.
And this is something commercial
systems like ESRI, have been,
you know have gone this way, okay?
But again the main point is that modeling
multiple relationships is difficult and
we illustrated that by showing
you the example of turn, okay?
Now another implication is that you know,
if you take a single spatial road,
you know, spatial network,
such as a road map, then it has, you know,
many, many different relationships.
And depending on your workload, or
your application, the priorities of those
relationships may be different, okay?
So depending on, you know,
your favorite relationship,
the graph model will also change.
Okay, so for the same roadmap you
may see many different graph models.
And we're going to show
you a couple of those.
The first one is the traditional one,
okay, where the nodes represented
road intersections, and
the edges represented these road segments
connecting edges and road intersection.
Okay, this is a very popular one.
And if you need to learn
only one graph model for
road maps this is the one
I will recommend, okay?
But we did see another choice.
You know,
if you were to model turns, okay,
if you really were really interested in
modeling turns, you were working for UPS.
And that's what, you know, your
application was to minimize left turns
then what we could do is to use
edges to model turn relationships.
But then your nodes may switch from
road intersections to road segments,
because turns are relationships between
road segments, which are adjacent, okay.
Of course, you know,
you can have a third one, and
this model will remind you of the model
we used for the river network.
You know, we could use,
actually, other types of nodes.
So, for example, like, streets and
avenues may be thought of as roads.
And the relationship may
be that intersects, okay?
Now this kind of a model
is sometimes used for
cartographic generalizations of road maps,
okay?
So if you have a very large city,
you know,
with many, many roads and
then you have to zoom out, and you
have to only show a subset of the roads
otherwise your picture may be cluttered.
So in order to identify the major roads,
which should be shown, this third
representation may be of interest.
Because you often prefer
the roads which have,
which cover many other smaller streets,
you know, which they intersect with, okay?
So again, to summarize what we
looked at were conceptual and
information models for roadmaps.
And we saw that at a detailed information
level called entity-relationship diagram
where we can represent many,
many concepts in roads,
such as streets, road intersections,
you know, road segments, turns, et cetera.
Then we looked at graph models which
are nice clean mathematical model and
also have been used in computer science
to design many scalable algorithm.
And we looked at the pros and
cons of graph models.
So even though it has very
nice mathematical and
computational properties,
it has limitations.
It can only model one relationship.
And you have to choose which one.
Okay?
And based on your application, if you
are doing cartographic generalization you
may choose nodes and edges in one way.
If you are doing some shortest path,
you may choose them in a different way.
So, with this,
we'll wrap up the discussion of
conceptual models of street networks.
When we come back, in the next segment,
we will look at logical models and
look at query languages for,
spatial networks.
And then we'll follow it up with
another video on the physical model,
the data structures and
algorithms of spatial network.
So look forward to seeing
you in the next few videos.
Thank you.