Welcome back to the discussion
of spacial computing.
Today, we are going to meet Dr.
Dev Oliver who has a computer science PhD.
And he works with ESRI,
Environmental Systems Research Institute,
a company you have seen
before in our lectures.
This company puts out a very popular
family of products called Arc GIS and
affiliated products.
Which are used by millions
of people in the world.
And in some sense it
was starting mid 1960s,
this company has been really spreading
the word in popularizing the technology.
So, le, let's come and meet Dev.
Hello Dev.
[LAUGH]
>> Hey how you doin?
>> Oh great.
It's very nice to see you again.
>> It's good to see you again
thank you for having me.
>> Great.
Great and thanks for
taking the time to talk to all the
students in this spatial computing MOOC.
I think they can, you know, share your
enthusiasm about spatial computing.
And learn about some of the, the real
things that you are doing at ESRI.
So first I wanted to ask you that,
you know, you have a broad
computer science background.
how, how did you,
get into spatial computing and
how did you get started there?
>> Well, from spatial computing,
from general computer sciences,
spatial computing.
The thing that draw, drew me was
the applications that were available.
So I remember using writing applications,
applications for
crayon mapping, applications for
outlaw detection and so on and.
Thinking this is wonderful, I want to
understand how these things work and
what are the underlying technologies.
So that's, that was sort of my pull
>> Wo, wonderful, and recently you moved
to a new area, in a Redlands, California.
With you know, as you joined ESRI.
Did you get to use any GIS
applications during your move?
>> Absolutely.
I was using Google maps and
other online services just to try
to figure out where things are.
Looking for houses.
I'm using Zillow.
I'm using a lot of different spatial
technologies that are out there.
So it's just, spatial computing
is a part of my every day life.
I can't do anything without,
without really.
Every day I use it.
>> Wonderful.
So, so now as a spatial
computing professional with
an inside ESRI what kind of projects
are you working on now days?
So within ESRI,
I'm working on two primary projects.
The first has to do with spatial networks.
I'm working on a project for
a facility network.
And basically, it is providing
analytic capabilities, indexing.
Database capabilities to utility
companies such as electric, water,
gas, things of that nature, so that is
one, one aspect that I'm working on.
I've always been interested in
spatial networks, such as road and
transportation networks.
Now I get to work on spatial
networks in a different context.
And this builds utility.
And the other job I'm working on is
a big data project here at ESRI.
So how can we sort of scale these
things up to larger data sets?
sort of the the focus of that project.
>> Okay, wonderful.
So spatial networks is something we
are discussing in this spatial MOOC.
You know, very basic around road networks.
How they are modelled at least
from academic perspective.
And I believe you are familiar with the,
the textbook Chapter 6 on
spatial network in my book.
So could you maybe say a little bit
more on, you know, the way spa,
the database book, spatial database
book describes spatial network.
And the way ESRI's own software
think about spatial network.
What are the commonalities and
what are some differences?
>> So commonalities would include
the way spatial networks are modeled,
for instance.
I would say, you would model it using
like, a basic underline graph, and so on.
But the difference is even in, even in
the commonalities they are difference is.
At ESRI, they tend to be, the model and
a little bit more richer.
They try to capture different aspects that
are important to the utility companies and
so on, so.
An example be for instance if you have
features that are coincident,
>> Mm-hm.
>> Usually you know, in our,
in a traditional setting, doors would
be the features that are connected.
You go from edge a to b,
point a to point b on an edge, to point c.
>> Mm-hm.
>> But
maybe we can bring in other ideas such as
logically connecting entities rather than
just based on their physical coincidence.
So, they are, you know, the,
the basics are the same.
But there are some other things that,
from other directions the company
is trying to go into as well.
That's an example.
>> Wonderful.
So, maybe another, you know,
related questions, would be, what,
what are the software products ESRI
puts out to manage spatial networks.
So right now there is a net,
there is a geometric network
package that's available.
And I'm currently working on software
that is that is not out there yet.
But that was previewed at a user
conference this year in San Diego.
So, working with geometric network is a,
is an example of a software that.
Where that's currently out there
on the market, but it's not very.
I'm working on the one that
is going to succeed that one,
kind of eventually, over time.
We'll see.
By the way, I can't really claim anything,
I bought the,
the products and store
>> No, we, we understand.
[LAUGH].
Yeah, I understand you may have some
restrictions on what you can share.
But, you did mention the user conference,
right?
Each summer ESRI brings,
their users together.
And I assumed you attend this, this year.
So, how many people were
there at that conference, and
why should somebody come and
attend that, you know?
Okay.
>> So there's that this conf, this conf,
if you're into spatial computing,
you want to be at this conference.
This year, we had 16,000 people.
>> Wow.
16,000.
>> 16,000, yes.
Very vast, diverse backgrounds in,
in spatial computing.
So, yeah, we want to come
just to connect with people.
You want to see what
they're technologies are.
I want to understand what the problems
that real users are having, in,
in general, and not just related to ESRI.
But just in general whatever the real
world, problems they're trying to solve.
And, this is a great environment for that.
>> Yeah, well, won, wonderful.
Now going back to the big data
project you are working on,.
So we just saw that, you know,
White House had an announcement
on big data for climate.
And in fact,
Jack Dangermond from ESRI was there.
And he pledged a lot of help from ESRI.
So, can you tell us a little bit more
on the spatial big data projects
you're working on.
>> So [LAUGH].
The, the current, so
basically I am very limited in what I can
say about the spatial big data project.
Only to say that there is an open
source ESRI on Hadoop that is
available through GitHub right now, and
it offers, spatial indexing capabilities.
>> Okay.
>> Spatial data types for
big data on Hadoop.
>> Wonderful.
>> So that is currently one
thing that the team is going in.
>> And this.
So this is GIS on Hadoop right?
This is GIS on Hadoop, correct.
And this an active project
that's been contributed to.
>> Wonderful.
>> That would be a good starting place.
>> So, so do you think is that a big
prominent future directions for
spatial computing?
>> In general, I would say yes that
is a prominent spatial direction.
How do you, future direction for
spatial computing.
How do you draw large quantities
of spatial temporal data?
>> Okay.
>> How do you visualize it?
How do you analyze it?
These are some of the,
the big challenges that are
>> Okay.
>> Out there in this community right now,
as I see it.
>> Yeah, great.
So what are some other future
directions for spatial computing?
>> So, there are many.
But the one that I,
I kind of see popping up is,
sort of these analytic setups tailored
toward very specific domains.
An example would be, taking traditional
analytics techniques such as hotspots.
And tailoring them to, say,
road networks or to arbitrary shapes.
Rings, polygons, different types of things
like that, that suit a particular domains.
So, this is sort of another
angle that I see is is,
is coming in the future or
is probably even here already.
>> Already.
[LAUGH].
Wonderful, thank you so much, Dev.
You know and it's a coincidence that this
MOOC also has about 16,000 students.
Which is roughly similar to the number
of people coming to the conference.
>> [LAUGH]
>> So
I really appreciate you taking your time.
And sharing this gorgeous
weather in Redlands, California.
>> It was my pleasure.
>> We can see outdoors picture [LAUGH].
>> Please come, please come to
Redlands one day if you can.
[LAUGH].
>> Wonderful,
you know and hopefully, if time permits.
You know, we'll probably get
some of your engagement or
advice on the discussion
group in this MOOC.
>> Absolutely.
>> Thank you, Dev.
>> You're welcome.
[SOUND]