Welcome back to the discussion
of spatial networks.
In previous few videos, we looked at the
motivation for spatial network in terms of
location based queries in urban areas
where transportation networks and
roadmap constraint our day to day movement
then we went you know, under the hood.
We looked at conceptual data models
including intraday relationship diagrams.
As well as graphs.
We also looked at logical data models,
particularly query languages.
How we added new statements,
like connect with and
with recursive to query graphs for
connectivity of shortest path.
Now we are going to go even
closer to the computer platform.
In, in the terms of
physical data model and
look at data structures and algorithms.
So this particular video will
focus on data structures, and
after this particular video, we should
be able to list at least a couple of
common data structures representing
graphs in main memory.
We should also be familiar with
a couple of file structures which
represent graphs on disks.
And possibly compare them, okay?
So again, here is the big picture.
Remember, we talked about conceptual
data models such as graphs and
entity relationship diagrams.
Logical data model, query languages.
And now we are really going
into physical data model,
very close to implementation
in performance.
And the goal is to look
at storage structure.
Next video we'll come back and
look at algorithms, okay?
So without further ado,
let's look at a simple graph which is
shown on the bottom left and
if you remember, there are six nodes.
1, 2, I'm sorry, 5 nodes.
1, 2, 3, 4, and 5.
And there are six edges.
So for example, node 1, from there we can
go to 2, from 2 we can go to 3, and so
on, okay?
So if we were to represent this in main
memory using simple data structures,
there are two common representations.
The first is based on matrices.
And you may have come across
matrices also in mathematics.
And in this case we won't need
to define rows and columns.
So for this particular graph a simple
representation uses nodes for
both rows and for columns.
So here is a matrix which has five rows,
one, sorry five columns one per node and
five rows.
1 per node.
Okay?
To represent edges,
we can use matrix entries.
So if you think about this entry 1, this
may represent an edge from node 1 to 2.
So this edge 1 to 2 is repre,
represented as matrix entry in first row,
second column.
Okay?
More abstractly.
If we look at an entry in row A and
column B,
this will be one only if we have
an edge from node A to node B.
Okay.
If it is 0 means there is no edge, okay?
So using this we can represent
the information and you can yet you know,
also query.
If I want to know all the edges
that are going out of a node.
Then we could look for a particular row.
So for example first row shows me all
the edges going out of node 1, okay?
If I want to know about all
the edges which are incident,
which are incoming to a particular node,
we'll look at columns.
So for example first column, shows you all
the edges which are coming into node 1.
So in other words there is only one edge.
From 5 to 1.
That is incident on one, okay?
And once you have this representation
you can use matrix algorithms.
So if you remember some of
your matrix operations,
such as matrix multiplication we
can form that repeatedly again and
again and again to get
connectivity kind of information.
Now in, computer science, there is another
very common representation which is
based on our adjacency list.
So if you have programmed references or
pointers in languages like JAVA,
C++ or C, people often
use that kind of representation to
make an adjacency list data structure.
And which may look like this, so here you
notice the list is a list of nodes, so
all five nodes are in a list, maybe node 1
is first, node 2 is second and so on, and
then with each of this nodes we attached,
ere, a list of.
Successive nodes, okay?
In other words if you,
let's say you are standing at node 1 there
are two outgoing edges to node 4 and 2.
So four and two are successors and
they are listed, you know,
just after one to represent the two edges.
The edge from node 1 to 2 and
the edge from 1 to 4 okay?
This kind of data structure is often,
agin useful to,
to find out all the successors or
predecessors of a particular node okay.
In this case successors are easier.
Predecessor is a little bit harder but
you can do that okay good.
So this is the life in main memory and
many of you may have take other
computer science courses or
done programming er, you know.
Code in Java and so
on where you use this data structure.
When you go to disk,
the story changes a little bit.
On disk we often think in terms of tables.
And in terms of disk blocks.
So let's first look at a table
representation of this graph.
In the traditional relational databases,
people often use normalized tables.
Where each sell is an atomic value.
And if we were to adhere to that kind of
a representation, we will need two tables.
We may have a table for nodes,
and another table for edges.
The node table may have node ID as well
as more node properties at this location.
The edge table, again,
may have the start node end node for
the edge, and then edge length or
other properties, okay?
Now oftentimes, the shortest fat
algorithms are run in a specialized
environment outside databases, and
they prefer a denormalized representation.
And in this case,
we actually merged the two tables into one
because we know that often times when we
are at a node in a graph we often
want a list of all successive nodes.
Okay.
So this other representation looks
very similar to the [INAUDIBLE]
list we just saw in main memory.
So he had noticed that in this
particular table there are five rows.
One per node.
And for each node we have
listed the successor nodes.
As well as predecessors.
And this table is often preferred,
over the normalized version for
shortest path [INAUDIBLE].
Okay.
There is another challenge on the,
you know, disk environment.
And that's why, you know,
instead of using the word.
Data structures.
People sometimes use the word
file structures when we refer to
storage on the disk.
And this challenge is to essentially
partition your file across disk blocks.
You know if, many of you know that the
unit of access on disk is not in terms of
words, but it is in terms of disk
blocks which may be kilobytes.
So, in other words, even if you
need the successor of one node,.
You know, that may represent only,
let's say, 100 bytes, but
the disk will send you a kilobyte anyway.
Okay?
So you will do lot more work.
So you might as well group the records,
which are likely to be accessed
together in the common disk pages.
Okay?
So this is a central problem when you
store data on disk.
Okay?
So in case of graph.
We can show you two ways to divide
up a graph into disk pages.
And try to see, you know,
how we can rank them.
So let's suppose we have a different
graph here with 16 nodes.
And then, you know,
some of these edges, okay.
So, and these are, these nodes
are embedded in a geometric space.
So you can think of latitude and
longitude or x y coordinates, okay.
So how should we divide
it up into disk pages.
And let's for simplicity assume that each
disk page can hold four nodes, okay?
You can divide it geometrically you know,
which is shown in the second figure.
So here all the red four nodes go to one
page, green 4 go to other, blue 4 go to
other and so on, and it's called
geometric partitioning because you have
taken a vertical line and a horizontal
line to cut up the graph into four pages.
And incidentally this is the dominant way
to deal with data and spacial databases.
If you think of our tree, quad tree,
grade file, they all think like that.
Okay?
Now, one of the insights
in this space is to
say that really another
partitioning may be multi table.
Which doesn't follow geometry.
But instead it looks
at the graph edges and
try to cut as few edges as
possible as shown here.
So now this area, notice here that
the green nodes are together.
Red nodes are together.
Brown are together.
And you don't have a very, you know,
strict kind of geometric partitioning.
But what is being done is you
notice these yellow edges.
And they are the ones which
go across the disk pages, and
we are trying to reduce them.
So in this case, you see the,
the cut edges are 1, 2, 3, 4 and 5.
Whereas, the geometric had many more.
It had seven, okay?
So, one of the insights is
that graph computations,
they often access information
by connectivity, that is, edges.
And if all edges are equally
likely to accessed,
then they would prefer
geometric partition.
If there is a non-uniform distribution,
then you may prefer partitioning, which
minimize the sum of weights on [INAUDIBLE]
To give you a more bigger picture.
You know here is, are, is the road map,
major roads in Minneapolis, and
we are showing you two ways to
partition it across disk blocks.
And in this case, the white edges
are showing you the cut edges, okay?
So you may want to pause the video
here for a second or two and stare at
these pictures and check which picture,
we don't, between the left and right.
Which one has less white, okay?
And that's the one which
has fewer cut edges.
And that's the one which will reduce
disk I/O for graph queries, alright?
And in this case, you know,
hopefully we will agree that on
the right side you have fewer white and
that will be preferable.
'Kay.
So, The last activity in this
module is a small exercise.
So, let's look at this simple network
which we have seen before in terms of
languages and so on.
And this has six nodes and few more edges.
And we'd like you to consider different
ways to partition this network
across disk pages.
And rank these partitionings
by the cut-edges.
Okay?
So suppose.
You know you could partition it like this.
So nodes 1, 2, and 3, these are together,
and you may cut these edges.
Right?
Or you might have 2, 3, 4 together,
so which are these 2, 3,
4 and you might cut these edges,
and so on.
So you may consider these partitionings.
Count the number of edges cut,
and suggest which is most
preferred to reduce your cost.
Okay?
To wrap up this video, you know,
we looked at main memory data structures.
And disc based file structures,
for storing road maps and
other spatial networks.
And one of the insight was that we
should minimize the edges cut by
disc partitioning.
To reduce your cost.
Okay?
In the next video we'll come back and
look at graph algorithms and which may use
this data structures to answer
connectivity of shortest path query.
So look forward to seeing you then.