Welcome back to the discussion
of spatial networks.
In particular the query languages for
spacial networks.
In past few videos,
we have looked at the motivation for
spatial networks, such as the navigation
apps that all, we all use on smartphone.
We also looked at conceptual models such
as entity/relationship diagram, as well
a graphs, you know, graphs have nice
mathematical and computational properties.
And we also discussed why,
the query languages that we've learned so
far, particularly from the previous
chapter, are not adequate, so
we need to learn new statements.
We did learn one new statement CONNECT By,
which is, which was in last video.
In this video, we're going to learn
another one called, WITH RECURSIVE,
which is part of SQL3 standard, and,
widely available through products.
Okay.
So, at the end of this video, we should
all be able to describe this RECURSIVE or
WITH RECURSIVE statement in SQL3, and
also use it to query graphs, Okay.
So, here is a quick background.
Again, formerly, you remember that
the special query languages that we
studied earlier were simple.
They were based on relational algebra and
some user defined data types.
And they at least
the relational algebra based on
SQL could not compute transitive
closure in the shortest path.
. Okay? So, we need it to extend this SQL
and people could do in different ways.
One could add new abstract data types.
Now, all these data types such as points,
polygons do not include graphs and parts.
Okay?
They do not include operators
like shortest path.
But if we were to design
new abstract data type and
add it to SQL3,
that could support graph kind of queries.
The other option is to
use custom statements.
We learned one of those in the last video,
in the CONNECT, and
we are going to learn the,
WITH RECURSIVE in this video.
Okay?
So, without further edu,
let's look at the inputs and
outputs of WITH RECURSIVE statements.
In times of inputs,
the first input is similar to the one for
CONNECT, which is the graph.
Okay?
So, we need to have a table,
which represents the edges of the graph.
Okay?
So, for example,
this set of edges may represent a graph of
this kind, where it lets node one to two,
there is an edge,
which is the first row, and so on.
Okay.
Now, given that the output
is a transitive closure, so
we can compute predecessor,
successors and so on okay?
But in terms of input WITH RECURSIVE
actually takes two additional sub queries,
so in other words it's a nested query.
The first sub query des,
describes ways to initialize the result.
So, we can take this table odd
as input and say that the result
may be initialized was this table itself
or a subset arose from the table.
The second query explains
how to grow the result.
So, starting from some basic values, which
is specified by the initialization query,
how do we add more rows to the result,
okay?
So, using these facilities you know,
can ex-compute predecessors, successors,
and you can actually do little bit more.
You can also go ahead and compute shortest
path and things of that kind, okay?
So, to give you a quick example, you know,
here are the three parts of WITH RECURSIVE
statement and we will illustrate each.
So, the first part, usually,
is the name of the result table and
the columns in the result table, and
that follows the key word WITH RECURSIVE.
So, in this case,
the result will be a table named X, and
this table has two columns, source and
the other column is destination.
So, the table structure is pretty
much similar to the input that we
saw before in this case.
But if you wanted we could have
other structure, for example,
you could choose only one of these columns
as we saw with the CONNECT statement.
The second part is a sub query,
which tells us how to initialize
the result, you know, named X.
So, in this case, this query is
something you have seen before.
So, if you only concentrate on
the SQL query inside the blue box,
then you can probably tell that
the result is initialized by
simply copying this input to edge table R,
okay?
The third part is the recursive query.
So, given some initial result,
how do we grow it?
And it is shown here, and notice that
this is a recursive query, okay?
So, some of you have done recursive
programming in computer science before or
in mathematics.
And, essentially recursion means
that you are defining something
using the same thing.
So, for example here,
result X is being defined.
But notice that the part of
the definition uses X, right?
So, this result X is defined in terms
of itself, and that's called recursion.
So let's at least look at this example
to understand how it works, okay?
But you know, in all recursions,
you have to have a base case and
that's this blue part, in order for
this recursion to end.
Okay?
All right, so, so
we at least now saw that syntax.
And in this syntax, really if you
build on your old SQL knowledge,
then there is only you know,
a very little new part.
The new keywords are WITH RECURSIVE,
you follow the result
table name in its columns.
Then there is another keyword S,
then you followed with a SQL
query to initialize the results.
Then, this union operator is also
something we know from before.
It just takes two tables and merges them.
And then there is a last part,
which is another subquery, which is
a select statement to grow the result.
Okay.
So, so, let's look an example input and
output, and
then we can see an execution trace to,
to to appreciate it even more.
So, example input could be a simple graph,
which is shown here with five notes and
five edges.
But it's presented in a tabular form
that's shown on the right as table R.
Okay, the output, you know,
so this is, this is sort of here in for,
the output X is another table,
which has two columns, so in this case,
your output table is shown here.
It just happens to have source and
destination columns specified here.
So, it's very similar
to input in this case.
And graph theory perspective,
it is actually a richer sect of ages.
So, if I can reach you know,
node 4 from node 1,
via multiple other edges, then there
is a direct edge from 1 to 4 here okay,
as we discussed in transitive closure.
All right, so let's take a look at
the meaning of this statement, and
one way to specify meaning is via
providing a hand executing procedure.
Okay?
So, in order to computer result X,
we start with the initialization query.
And if you remember the que,
the initialization query, it
was simply copying source and data columns
from import table R to the result table X.
So, if we did that,
then these five rows from the input table
will get copied to the output table X.
Okay.
Once we have done that, we are going to
grow the result using the recursive step.
So, again recall what
the recursive step was.
And in recursive step, we try to match
the destination column of input table,
that's this column,
to the source column of result table.
So, if as long as there is a match between
destination here and source in the result,
we can add new rows okay.
To rephrase it, we can say it as follows.
We can say that in case you had a row
a,b in R, okay, such as let's say 1,2.
And you had another row b, c in X,
such as this, let's say, two, three.
If that happens, then you can essentially
say, look, you know, in the original
result, we can go from one to two, and in
result table, we can go from two to three.
So, we can add a row from one
to three in the result table.
Okay?
To give you more specific example,
here it is okay?
So R has 1 2 X has 2 3, right,
R has 1 2 and X has 2 3.
And in this case,
R's destination matches X's source, so
we could add a new edge,
1 3 to result, okay?
And that's shown as here,
so we added 1 more, okay.
We can find similar, you know, other pairs
from R and X, to add more information.
So, for example, you notice that
in import table you had 2 3.
And its destination matched
the source of 3 to 4.
And when that happens,
now we can add 2 to 4 in the result.
Okay?
So, continuing on,
you can find other such pairs.
R has (5, 3), X has (3, 4).
So you can add (5, 4).
And then finally, R has (1, 5),
X has (5, 4), so you can add (1,
4) in that result table.
Okay?
And if after this,
if you try this procedure further, in
this example we are not going to get any.
So, this recursion continues
till the result stabilizes.
If we cannot add any more,
then the recursion ends and
at that time you have the full result.
So, this is your result table in SQL.
If you want to visualize it as a graph,
then it will look like this transitive
closure graph that we saw before.
And all the new rows we added
are these new edges that show up in
the transitive closure, okay?
So, to summarize, in SQL3,
a new statement with recursive
was added to support graph queries,
such as predecessor successors that we
saw before with connect by, but
also newer queries like shortest path.
And in this particular video we
saw the syntax of WITH RECURSIVE.
It essentially names the result
table in its columns.
It gives you a initialization sub query,
and
finally a recursive sub
query to grow the result.
Okay?
And this gives you a basic means to
write queries on the graph in SQL3.
Okay?
With this, we'll more or less wrap up the
discussion of query languages on graphs,
and in subsequent video we'll come back
and go to the physical data model.
Try to see the data structures which
are used to represent these graphs, and
also the actual algorithms
that a database may
keep to quickly execute graph
queries on large graphs.
Okay?
So, I look forward to seeing you in
the next videos on physical data model.
Thank you.
[SOUND]