Welcome back to the discussion
of spatial computing.
Today we are going to meet Dr.
Betsy George, at Oracle Spatial and
share and learn from her, you know the
excitement of spatial computing at Oracle,
a popular product which we have
mentioned several times in this course.
Okay?
So please say hello,
to Doctor Betsy George.
>> Hi.
>> So Betsy, you know the first question
we wanted to ask you is, you know,
coming from a broad mathematics and
computer science background, how did
you get started with spatial computing?
>> I came into spatial computing
through my interest in graph theory.
So graphs.
I have always been impressed with them.
Expressiveness and
the simplicity of the model called graph.
And so I got introduced to graphs
at the very early stage and
then, I was looking at, when I was
starting my research I was looking for
some real world applications of graphs.
>> Mm-hm.
>> So then I got introduced
to transportation networks,
which are basically spatial networks and
and my first familiarization
with transportation at work was through
a study of evacuation planning algorithms.
And so when I studied the problem,
a little bit,
I realized the challenges that the real
world application domains brought,
to this world of graph theory,
and I was really excited and
impressed by the way, we needed to
re-evaluate the algorithms with.
In terms of the assumptions that we made,
when we designed graph algorithms.
>> Okay.
>> We needed to reformulate them
to suit the applications better.
To be more specific in terms of the
evacuation planning algorithm the aim was
to evacuate the people as
fast as possible, so for a,
from the graph theory perspective,
that would immediately you know,
let me choose the shortest path, or the
fastest path, algorithm, and apply that.
But, then I realized that
that's not going to work,
because the roads have capacities and
you cannot push everybody to move,
along the same shortest path possible
from the source to the destination.
So, we needed to take care of the capacity
constraints, which is not really.
Taken into account in any of the,
shortest path algorithms that I knew of.
So that was one example, where graph
theory really met the real world
application and
that opened up a lot of possibilities for
interrogation of the assumptions that
we're behind the graph theory algorithms.
So.
To put it shortly, I was, I was,
I became interested in special
computing through special networks.
>> Okay.
>> And so then I started seeing the lot
of challenges that are raised by,
you know, the,
when you bring location into computations.
>> Okay.
>> And how to effectively use that, and
so, it's been,
it's been a really exacting journey.
We've started off, with spartial networks
which, which are like the real networks.
>> Oh.
Won, wonderful.
So in this course, you know,
we did discuss shortest path.
>> Okay.
>> And
I'm guessing lot of people in this course,
have used services like Google Maps.
>> Yes.
>> Or the GPS devices to find.
>> Sure.
>> Shortest path.
>> So, it,
it may be nice to kind of briefly,
you know, re you know,
revisit the evacuation scenario.
So let's say everybody living
in Boston had to leave.
>> Sure.
>> Because of a major hurricane.
>> And
if they all just went to Google, and
found shortest path to their destination,
maybe, in New York City or in Albany.
>> Yeah. [LAUGH] >> What would go wrong?
I mean, why not do that?
>> Oh, you you will see, like,
cars backed up all the way to
the place where you started.
[LAUGH] Because, you know?
Everybody's going to drive out, and-
>> Okay.
You know, if you ask them to
move the fastest route possible, then you
know, everybody's going to be there and
you know like the roads will get congested
and the traffic will get backed up.
So you have to take care of you know,
the capacity as
the roads get used more and more.The
congestion increases the traffic time,
the travel time gets increased so that
fastest pack itself changes based on that.
So, that had to be taken into account.
>> Okay
>> So somehow, so
that added a new dimension to
the [INAUDIBLE] algorithm, so.
>> So, so, I guess graphs have been
extended to model age capacity, as well,
so is there like a general
family of graph models which.
>> Yes
>> Capacity into account?
>> Yes you know, for example my
research was actually to look at the,
the changes that the,
the graph can change,
the whole assumption that the graph can
change as the network is getting used.
And so the temperature changes of
the graph needed to be taken into account,
in the algorithms themselves.
Like so when you do the computation,
you have to keep track of the changes.
>> Right.
>> That take place to the graph.
>> Okay.
>> So that brings in,
in the, the, the temporal graph concept.
And so the algorithms needed to
be re-examined, in that light.
>> Very wonderful.
And I think your encyclopedia
article on road networks,
is going to be one of
the supplementary readings,.
>> Okay. [LAUGH] >> For this course.
So hopefully,
some of that is going to relate back and
they can see the temporal part also.
That is wonderful.
So the next question, you know?
What kinds of things are you working
now a days at Oracle Spartial and
could you also tell us a little bit more
about Oracle Spartial from you know?
As perspective of somebody
working in the group?
>> So our special basically you know,
provides support for article,
for spatial data types.
You know, we do have like you know,
special data types.
Like we support coordinate systems and
and most, commonly used
spatial operations like you can find
nearest neighbors, you can you know the,
the fastest route from point A to
point B and stuff like that.
And also, we do have as
a part of the oracle spatial,
we do have a specialization
tool called Map Viewer.
Which is being extensively used to
visualise, maps and any spatial data for
that matter and I specifically work
in the network data model team, so
I was kind of fortunate enough to find
a job, which actually makes use of my
research and, you know, cool to actually,
like, carry my research into the industry.
So I.
work in the network data model team and
the network data model basically,
provides the facilities to represent
networks or graphs in the database.
And so there is a database
representation for networks.
And on top of that there
are analysis capabilities provided.
So most of the.
Most commonly used graph
operations are being
offered like weekend computer's pack.
>> Okay.
>> We do traveling salesman problem.
>> And then we do have the network
[INAUDIBLE] of the most
spatial operations.
Like you can find near this neighbors.
>> Okay But then cost analysis, drive time
polygons, all based on network costs.
>> Okay, so-
>> That is the basic thing
that our group does.
So what my specific work has been,
again, they're adding a temporal
dimension to the near data model.
>> How wonderful.
>> which it didn't have
a time aspect to it before.
>> Okay.
>> So, making the graphs time aware and
the com,
the network computations time aware.
Actually opens up a lot of possibilities.
For example, the simplest case would
be a traveling salesman problem.
And when you use them as a computing
trucking route to visit like four cities,
if you, if the application is time then we
can actually insist that the trucker get.
Visit a certain city,
in a certain period of time.
And sometimes, that becomes a necessity.
>> Like Russia and so on.
>> Yes, Russia was, and also,
there are some, you know, there are some
restrictions like, you need to visit this
particular place but on a certain day.
So you can actually can incorporate
that constraint, if Time of it.
Then, as we mentioned earlier,
the other application would be
incorporating time in such a way that
the graph itself is modified and
handled in such a way that it can change.
So the graph changes with time,
for example the condition.
So-
traffic data is out there, now, so.
We do have the facility to incorporate
the changes in the traffic volume as,
during, like at different times of day.
>> Oh, okay.
>> And,
based on that the travel time changes, so
we can actually compute the fastest
time if you start at 8 a.m.
in the morning
>> Oh, wonderful [INAUDIBLE].
[LAUGH]
>> Versus, like, in the midnight.
>> Okay.
>> And you might even get two
different roads when you compute these two
different roads at two different times.
>> [INAUDIBLE].
So, so
I am basically focusing more on the the
temporal aspect of the network data model.
We also have a little
bit of a support form of
routes which again brings in time
because everything is schedule based.
So you already kind of gave answer to
the next question I was going to ask.
[LAUGH] Which was, so, you remember
chapter six in the Spatial Database book,
which had a very basic model of,
transportation networks and
tons of graphs.
So the basic question was,
when you see the.
Graph model or the spatial electric
model in our electric space vehicle,
versus what you see in
the [INAUDIBLE] textbooks,
what are the things which are common and
what are the things which are different?
>> The basics of the common,
the basics are very common,
we do have nodes that are just nodes and
legs, so we do have entities which are.
Represented by nodes, like which could
be like intersections of roads or
like cities.
But and also like we do have
connections between nodes.
They can be any relationship.
So in the case of a road network if.
One node is reachable from another node,
we connect them through using an edge or
a link.
So in the basic debt work
data model in article on,
so like, we do have node table, which is
a database at a percentage of nodes and
the link table which actually provides
the connectivity between nodes and but.
Right now.
The things is, like you know?
The, the text book model actually
treats the graph as static.
>> Okay.
>> Nothing changes.
>> So,
you do have one edge between node one and
node two.
And you actually.
Have one parameter called
cost on that link.
So the underlying assumption is
that the cost doesn't change.
>> Okay.
>> But
we do have a mechanism right now
to actually represent the cost in
such a way that it actually shows
a variation with respect to time.
>> That's wonderful.
>> So that is, that is one of the most
striking differences I would say.
It has.
>> Indeed, indeed, wonderful.
And I think your encyclopedia article
gives a little glimpse of that.
>> Sure.
Wonderful.
Now looking ahead, you know,
next five to seven years, what
are the major directions in Oracle Spatial
and you know, in your own networks module.
>> I think, when I think about it in
a very generic way I think like you know,
to go more on.
To kind of like,.
Expand more on this
changing graph paradigm.
People are collecting data every day.
And you know, like in a, if you use a, you
know, an online navigation system like,
and everybody's like, saying that okay.
If I don't take this road because
it's congested and, you know,
this is the travel time and, you know, so.
And, and big companies like no,
Nokia's like putting data out there.
So, there is a lot of data coming in.
>> Okay.
>> And so.
We need to some how
incorporate this into our
computations to make
computations more meaningful.
>> Okay.
So I think we need to have a mechanism
to somehow use this data meaningfully,
but at the same time it's the volume
is growing so drastically.
So we need to do somehow make
the computation section.
So I think big data is here, you know so
that I think that,
that is going to sort of like.
Creeping every where.
>> Yeah. Okay. >> So,
we need to explore that.
>> Okay.
>> And how we
can actually incorporate the big data
analytics into network competition.
Which is not that easy.
>> Okay.
>> Because networks are not that easily.
Partitioned, you know, sensibly.
So we need to figure out how to
partition networks sensibly, so
that we don't have too much communication
going on between the nodes.
>> Okay.
>> And,
also that we don't sacrifice
too much of accuracy.
Mining is a different issue,
because I think mining, you know,
as long as you find out the trends, it's
okay, but with networks, you know it's.
Still a tough problem how to let.
And then also like we need to
adopt our algorithms also to
sort this big data paradigm.
We need to figure how to do that and
even if we don't move into that.
You know,
as the value of the data increases.
It is basically, and
also even just bringing in time
kind of complicated everything.
>> You explode the data volume, right.
For each instance you may have
a replication of that network.
>> Yeah.
Yeah, and so it is basically, and
also like we cannot apply
the old algorithm techniques.
>> Okay.
Okay.
>> You know, most of the assumptions
that we made with respect to the old.
>> Design can not be applied when
time comes then because most fo
the properties that we relied on to
apple these techniques are breaking.
>> Right.
>> And for example,
like in program to find the best.
>> [INAUDIBLE] to answer
the question where to start.
So I [CROSSTALK].
>> Oh wow.
So, we did,
we did talk about [INAUDIBLE] and A stars,
so what happens to those
when you add time?
>> Because [INAUDIBLE] basically depends
on a property called greedy property, and
which actually depends on a sub-optimal
structure, in, of the final solution,
which breaks when.
When we actually extend
the shortest path question to,
when is the best time to start so
that I spend the least time on the road?
You know, so we are actually talking about
optimising it across, on the graph and
across time too.
So when that comes in, the greedy property
doesn't, is not satisfied anymore.
So I cannot extend.
Extra easily.
>> Yeah, wonderful.
>> yes.
>> Sounds like lot
of interesting opportunities in.
>> Yes.
>> In the area for, or the room for
this area to grow.
>> Yes, for a researcher, yes.
[LAUGH]
>> [LAUGH] Wonderful.
So thank you so much Vetsi/b for you know
taking the time to talk to our audience.
And you are in really a sweet spot
where you can look at the research and
also you can bring it to
an influential product.
Which is now being used by really,
really large number of people so.
>> Thank you, thank you for
giving me this opportunity.
This is such an honor and you know, a
great honor to be a part of this project.
Thank you.
>> Thanks.
>> Thank you.
>> Wonderful so so
this was Doctor Betsy George.
A principle in a member technical
staff at Oracle Special.
And in a lot of thing she talked about we
covered in the module on spatial network.
This is a field which all ready
has many applications and
as you heard looks like there will
be many more in coming years.
And hopefully some of the people in
this course will be participating and
shaping this field in the near future.
Thank you and next interview we'll meet
a few of the researchers in this area.