Welcome back to the discussion of spatial
network query processing and algorithms.
In the last video, we saw the big
picture of query processing.
Databases often like to
have a few building blocks,
which are frequently used.
And for each building block,
they like to have multiple algorithms, so
that they can pick and choose.
In the last module, we also saw
algorithms for connectivity query.
And in this module, we will try to look at
two algorithms for shortest path queries.
So at the end of this module, we should
be able to name those two algorithms and
also compare their, you know, behavior.
So in terms of shortest path, you know,
the basic common algorithm
is an iterative algorithm.
It goes into a loop, and in,
in each iteration of the loop,
it essentially looks for
most promising direction.
And so it keeps a set of descent
which we have visited so
far, and it picks the most promising one.
But the ranking differs
between the algorithms.
So if we started with the older algorithm,
Dijkstra's Algorithm then it picks
up the closest descendent to self.
It may not look intuitive, but
its a general algorithm it works in many,
many graphs.
Okay?
Now A star which came from artificial
intelligence, you know, may look a little
smarter and it tries to pick a descendent
which is closest to the destination.
Right?
And you might wonder why Dijkstra do that?
And the answer is, you know, in some sense
its not that easy to figure out which
descendent is closest to the destination
because the future is not known.
We don't know if, you know,
there are the shortest path or
the most direct paths may be broken.
Right?
You may have to go around an obstacle.
So in case of A star, you need some
heuristic to kind of do this focusing and
that becomes very domain dependent.
Fortunately for us,
such heuristics are easy for
road maps, because they are embedded
in Euclidean space and straight line
distance estimations has the right
set of property to make A star shine.
But in general, if you are in some
other networks, like electricity
distribution and so on you know, it might
be worthwhile to look at both algorithms.
Okay.
So essentially, you know, we looked at
that the most promising descendent and
then once we visited that descendent,
we can update the path to that descendent.
And in addition, you know,
we may find an additional descendent
which our Dijkstra will reach from there.
Okay.
So we keep looping,
till the destination node is expanded.
Till that becomes the most promising node,
and
at that time, we have found shortest path.
So, let's first look at the behavior, and
we can later on look at the exemption or
why this is correct and so on.
So, so we are going to show
you a small animation.
Let's supposed we have this very
simple graphic, a greedy graph.
Again, not really unrealistic.
If you live in Manhattan or some other
downtowns there are grids like this.
Maybe a few more is
likely we're not showing.
And in this, suppose we
are starting from this red node,
which is B and trying to go to this
upper right node, the green one.
Okay.
So
we are going to show you the behavior
of Dijkstra's and A star side by side.
So in the first iteration,
they behave very similarly.
They both start from the red node and
they list their neighbors.
There are three neighbors here.
And at A star only only two
are shown as yellow, but
it also will look at this lower left one.
So all immediate neighbors are considered,
okay?
The behavior changes
in the next iteration.
Now if you think about, you know,
what Dijkstra's will do,
it's going to pick one of these neighbors
which is closest to the start node.
And in this case,
they're all pretty much tight.
You can pick any one of them
in the case of Dijkstra's.
But in case of a star, these two neighbors
are closer to destination the green one,
than this particular lower left one.
Right?
So,
A star is going to pick one of these two,
it will never pick that.
Okay?
So, once they have made their choices,
they will visit Dartnord and
Ardmore neighbors.
So in case of A star, the only thing
that will be added is this node
because that's what, you know,
it's connected to here.
And, you know based on that,
this isn't added because also
closest to the destination.
So these notes are also
connected to other nodes, but
if you look at the total distance,
this one will win out.
Okay?
Where as Dijkstra can only
see the distance to self,
it doesn't know which of these
nodes is closest to destination.
So it can pick any one of them, so
we have shown all of them in yellow.
Okay.
The next iteration, it continues.
A star again, you see, is focused.
It's picking nodes which
are closer to the destination,
whereas Dijkstra is kind of going
in a breadth-first search manner.
So you go further, you know,
another iteration, and
now A star has actually
reached the destination.
Having expanded a small set
of nodes which all seem to be
somewhere near the straight line path.
Okay?
Whereas Dijkstra's still is ongoing and
it will have few [INAUDIBLE] till it
reaches, and you kind of see that it
has a more breadth-first search
behavior it looks at lot more nodes.
Okay?
Okay.
So once we have this sense, you know,
we can also try to quickly look at
the formal properties which
makes these algorithms work.
Okay.
So both of these algorithm, actually
follow a very general algorithm design
paradigm in computer computer
science called Dynamic Program.
You know, some of you probably
took algorithms course and
you probably know that paradigm.
Okay.
A special example of that
paradigm is Sub-path optimality.
So essentially, you know, road maps and
other transportation network,
they have some very nice properties.
They basically have the simple property
where edge costs are positive.
Okay.
You never have a negative distance.
They're additive, and they are also fixed.
Okay.
So we are ignoring time variation all
together here.
So under these properties,
essentially, if I look at a optimal
path from node A to B, and let's say,
it goes through C, then the sub-path
going from A to C will also be optimal.
And that's essentially underlies,
you know,
the basic behavior of this algorithm,
it guarantees optimality.
Okay.
In addition to this, for
A star you need one other property.
Remember, we have to guess, you know,
which, the, you know,
descendent is closest to destination, so
this guess usually comes in the form
of a heuristic mathematical function.
For example,
in Euclidean space like road maps,
you can estimate straight line
distance to be your guess.
Okay.
And that straight line distance has this
nice property of being under estimate.
Because you can never beat
straight line on a planar surface.
Right.
And you need that kind of a property for
A star to give you the correct solution.
And designing heuristic functions takes
effort, and they depend on the domain.
But fortunately, for spacial network the
straight line distance does pretty well.
Okay.
Great.
So this hopefully gives you a sense of
two shortest path algorithms, A star and
Dijkstra, they're both very popular.
But in addition,
people have gone further and
tried to cue in these algorithms
to become even faster.
People have added shortcuts and they
have looked at hierarchical algorithms.
And perhaps, through reading list or
another video,
we will give you a sense of some of those.
Okay.
Just to wrap up.
Again, this module we looked at shortest
part algorithm, and together with
the previous two modules, we gave you a
sense of physical data model which covers
data structures and algorithms underlying
the shortest path in connectivity theory.
Thank you and you know, hopefully
we'll see you in the next module.