Welcome back to the discussion
of spatial computing.
With this video,
we start a new module on Spatial Networks.
So at the end of the first
video we have two objectives.
All of us should be able to describe the
societal importance of spatial networks.
Why we are studying this,
who can benefit and so on.
And in addition, we also want to discuss
the limitations of spatial querying that
we discussed earlier in context of spatial
networks and their applications, okay.
So, let's first look at spatial
networks and where they come from.
A very classical use case is navigation.
So navigation pertains to finding
routes to a particular destination,
and that navigation is really you know,
as old as humans, right.
So, you know, when humans, they had
not settled down for agriculture and
so on, they still had to go find food and
water and other things.
And they had to probably remember routes,
very much like how elephants and
other migratory species do that today,
okay.
Once humans settled, then you will still
see the notions like treasure hunt, right.
Even Columbus, you know, when he came to
West Indies or what we call America today,
was looking for trade routes to
to get spices from India, okay.
So again, knowing the routes were very,
very important for different kind of
trades, and there were well known
routes like silk route over land and
people are finding routes over ocean.
Another important group which deals with
navigation a lot is you can say Defense or
Armed Forces, right.
So they again, need to have
many different kinds of routes.
So if they have a particular target,
they need to find a stealth route to
reach there without getting
detected by the adversary.
And even if they are not looking for
target if,
if just, you know, the units are placed
somewhere, they need to get food and
supplies to the troops and for
that they need supply routes.
So routes and navigations are, you know,
very, very core activities
in human society, okay.
But more recently, you know,
this has come to all of us and
you can probably recognize the next
set of examples much quicker, okay.
So probably, you know, many of you use
these navigation apps on smartphones.
Using which you can essentially find
a route to your friends place or
to work or school.
Before smartphone apps were popular,
we were also had dedicated devices,
sometimes called GPS devices.
So you kind of see a picture
of this GPS device.
People who go off-road, you know,
where you may not have cellphone signal
as readily available, may still use that.
So people who do hiking and boating,
they still use the dedicated devices.
And these devices are also being
imbedded in many other areas.
So for example, many modern cars
have a navigation system in their
instrument board and
people use that, okay.
So you probably know that, you know,
using these devices, you can very
easily find routes and locations, okay.
Also another platform is World Wide Web.
So beginning mid 90s,
you have services, such as MapQuest.
And in the last decade,
you have Google Maps.
So you could actually from
your desktop computer or
tablet, you know, go onto World Wide Web
and also do routing, okay.
So these things tell us
many different things.
So first, you know, if you are in a new
place and you just want to see what's
around you, they can display a map
around the current location.
And they can also compute inner distance.
They can find you routes to
a destination and so on, okay.
So navigation systems are often built
around what we call spatial networks.
For example, in these cases we
are looking at road networks.
But you could also use public
transportation, such as train and
so on and find routes across those, okay.
All right, so
let's let's look at another category
of application, which is very similar.
So broadly, what we saw in navigation
system audio smartphone app
are all, you know,
part of a general category of services
called Location Based Services, okay.
So within Location Based Services,
there are many different kinds of
questions that can be answered.
So very first question is,
where am I, okay.
In outdoor world,
one can get that through GPS, but
indoor there are other kind of sensors.
Okay, if you are you know,
in tunnel and so
on, they're may be different
sensors that tell you that.
But there is a very simple
software interface.
So using a simple function call,
we can find the location.
And these locations
come in multiple forms.
So most of us are used to symbolic
place names, so a street address.
The computer science building in
the University of Minnesota may have
a street address such as 200 Union Street,
Southeast Minneapolis, Minnesota 55455.
Or you may have another symbolic name
such as Mall of America and so on.
But there is anoth, a different
system which is numerical system.
So these symbolic street addresses can
be converted to numerical systems,
such as latitude, longitude.
So, if you are Goog, using Google Earth
web service, you will often see that.
And also if you have seen
the readings from your GPS, they
often start their life in this numerical
form, latitude, longitude as an example.
So these services also allow you to
translate between symbolic form,
such as street address and numerical form,
and that service is called Geocoding.
You could also go other way.
So if you just have a latitude,
longitude, you could ask then symbolic
place name for that particular place.
Maybe it's a well known point
of interest or a city, okay.
A second category of service is
broadly called directory service wh,
where you can ask what's around me.
So it could be as simple as asking for
nearest instance of a service.
Let's say, you want to locate a doctor or
clinic, you can go and ask for
nearest clinic from your current location,
or a particular location of choice, okay.
You can ask for a restaurant or,
you know, taxi and so on.
In addition,
you could also ask a range query so
you could essentially say, well, if I am
willing to walk a mile along the roads or
drive a mile what are the instances
of banks within a mile.
And you can then choose the ones
which is most convenient, okay.
And the last part of this is route okay,
which you have seen in
navigation quite a bit.
Once you have selected an instance of
a service, you can ask how do I get
there either walking or driving or through
public transportation and so on, okay.
And location based services as
a segment has been growing quite a bit.
Besides the consumer application there
are many, many business applications where
businesses ask questions
of their own interests.
And I will show some of those very
soon under network analysis, okay.
Okay, now going beyond the,
you know, the current consumer services
such as location based services.
You can ask who else in the society
cares about spatial networks and
the key thing to note,
which is what this slide is telling you.
Is that if you are in any urban area,
you know, there are many,
many very critical spatial
networks of interest, okay.
So, this is actually showing you critical
infrastructure listed by Department of
Homeland Security, and
let me point out some of them, okay.
Very first one was transportation,
which is what we had been talking about so
far but, you know.
Next, you can go look at energy,
if you think about electricity supply.
Okay, the electricity is carried through
different electricity network from
the generation capacity to your home.
And again, you know, people have
to keep track of that network for
many different reasons.
One of which is to protect
against adversaries, all right.
Or if, you know, certain fault happens,
if there was a storm and power lines went
down, they still need to track them on
geography and go repair them, okay.
So, you know, there are similar networks
for gas, the cooking gas that comes to
most houses again,
comes through a network of pipelines.
Oil is transported often
through pipelines.
Another network is water, okay.
In most urban areas,
the water is piped, right.
So there is a central
place where water tank or
water is located and
then it comes through pipes to all homes.
Even broader the, you know,
there are river networks and so on.
So, this water flows along different
networks that people have to monitor.
One last example, which many of
us relate to is communication.
We all use internet,
which is another kind of spatial network.
In past, people were not paying attention
to the locations of these switches.
But now,
there is a lot more awareness of that.
And particularly for cellphone, which can
move around if you want to tap internet.
Then, you know, your internet companies
have to keep track of where it is and
route things properly and
geography plays a role, and so on.
So essentially, if you are in
an urban setting, there are lots and
lots of these spatial networks
which are of interest.
And people, you know,
use them in different ways,
ask different questions, okay.
All right so, you know so
there are many societal applications.
Now the big question is, you know,
do we already know enough?
You know, we had a whole week on spatial
query, and we saw lots of spatial,
you know, data types and
different kind of querying in SQL.
And the big question is,
you know, does that already
cover all this spatial network?
Do we really need to spend another
week learning new computational ideas
here, okay.
So this slide essentially telling
you that, what we learned so
far is not adequate, okay.
So first, you remember, you know,
we learned OGIS Simple Feature Types which
provided us points, linestrings, polygons.
So, key thing to notice is that
those data types model geometry.
They do not model street
network very well, where you
need slightly different data types, you
know, as the mathematical model of graphs.
Okay, if you want to compute shortest
path, then you need those operators and
a new data type called graphs
which are missing, okay.
Same way in SQL, you know,
we learn joins and many different things.
But you have to realize that
shortest paths cannot easily be
expressed using these joins, okay.
They belong to a special category of
operations called transitive closure.
And there is a well known critical result
that your basic relational algebra or
basic SQL cannot expressive transitive
closure set as shortest path.
And I will show you many other
examples of that on the next slide.
Now there is some good news in SQL real,
starting SQL3 recursion was added,
which can allow you to express
some of these queries.
Of course, the performance is still
something people are working on,
but you can express some of
these queries there, okay.
So, let's go down and
look at these network analysis queries.
And this is now giving you
the business side of spatial network,
what many businesses do with this, okay.
So one part, you know, the first thing
businesses do is very similar to
what consumers do, which is routing, okay.
So often times, you know, let's say,
you know, a business has to ship some
item from a factory to a warehouse, and
they want shortest path for that, okay.
So that is very simple.
So they just wanted to know how to get
some items from factory to a warehouse.
But usually their queries
are a little bit more complex,
which some of us might have experienced.
That, you know,
they might not have one destination,
they have multiple destination, okay.
So these routes get a little
more combinatory and
interesting, because you may also have
to choose the order of destination.
So again, try to imagine, you know you may
have a warehouse eh, store like Sears or
Walmart, where many people came and they
ordered some appliances, like washers or
dryers, right.
Next, you know, morning, the drivers
basically get a collection of five or six
of these deliveries, and they have to go
and deliver that within couple of hours.
So it's important to know in which
order these should be delivered and
what route, okay.
So this is a very typical query.
Another query is in terms of allocation.
So many businesses has many,
many stores, right.
If you think about a post office, it has
many different locations, right, and
then they have many customers.
So a big question for them is to allocate
customers to service centers, okay.
And in, you know, reverse of this
is to designate service areas for
each service center, okay.
And finally, there is a third
question called site selection.
So let's say, they wanted to add a new
service center because customers have now
grown in a certain area.
Then, you know, they want to essentially
ask which are the best locations.
So that you might minimize distance to
the new customers to solve that, or
you might minimize some other things,
okay.
Now again, you know, this list of queries,
they all belong to this graph-based
questions, and almost all of them
include transitive closure recursion.
So expressing these using simple joins,
select and
project, what we learn in spatial
querying before, is not possible.
So we need to learn new things.
So as we go along in this chapter,
we'll learn about graph data types and
the algorithms and
how we handle these kind of queries, okay.
So again, to sum up, you know,
we talked about spatial networks,
their societal importance.
Who uses them and
we saw consumer applications, business
application, government application.
And we also discussed the limitations
of spatial querying in
supporting such questions.
And as the chapter goes by,
we'll come and learn new things
to represent these queries.
Thank you and I look forward to
seeing you in the next segment.
[NOISE]